"The Benefits of Turmeric Curcumin for Arthritis,
Blood Sugar, Cholesterol, and Body Weight"
The number of clinical trials
on turmeric—
not in rats or Petri dishes—
but with actual people
continues to climb—
dozens a year,
and most were randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled,
the gold standard
for clinical trials.
There have been
so many trials published
that there are now
umbrella reviews on turmeric.
You've heard of systematic
reviews and meta-analyses,
pooling multiple studies
together.
Well, an umbrella review
can be like a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of systematic reviews
and meta-analyses,
meaning pooling multiple
meta-analyses together,
placing them at the very top
of the hierarchy
of evidence pyramid.
Dr. Greger has covered
the benefits
of the turmeric pigment curcumin
for knee osteoarthritis,
in some cases working
as well as or even better
than anti-inflammatory drugs
and painkillers
without their side effects
of injuring our gut,
and in the ten years since,
a meta-analysis
of 11 meta-analyses
on the efficacy of curcumin
for relieving osteoarthritis
strongly supports
that it can relieve pain
as well as improve
joint mobility
and shorten medication use.
And more isn't
necessarily better.
Low-dose extracts
appear to have
similar pain relief effects
to high-dose extracts.
What about other
arthritic conditions?
A pilot study in 2012
of 45 patients
showed promise
for rheumatoid arthritis,
finding it is
actually more effective
at alleviating pain
compared to the leading drug.
And a recent meta-analysis
including
more than 500 patients
found the same:
curcumin was beneficial
both for inflammation levels
and clinical symptoms.
Curcumin's ability to lower
some inflammatory biomarkers,
like C-reactive protein,
a marker
of systemic inflammation,
extends more broadly
to patients
with autoinflammatory conditions
and the stronger effects
seemed to appear
at relatively smaller doses.
You may recall that Dr. Greger
talked about a 2012 study
in prediabetic individuals
where zero percent of those
taking curcumin extract
for nine months progressed
to type 2 diabetes
while 16% of those
on placebo did.
There have been
a lot of studies since.
Fourteen systematic reviews
and meta-analyses
containing 61 individual
randomized controlled trials
were included
in this umbrella review.
Fasting blood sugars and HbA1C,
a measure of longer-term blood
sugar control, both improved,
no matter what formulation
of turmeric or curcumin
was consumed,
but the quality
of the studies was low,
not including
important information
like their funding sources,
and the types of
turmeric/curcumin preparations
were wide ranging.
What if we want to know
the impact of turmeric alone,
not a special
curcumin formulation
that supplement companies
can charge us
a bunch of money for?
This dose-response
meta-analysis
breaks it out for us
with turmeric resulting
in better results
than curcumin-only treatments.
Note that benefit was found
for a variety of participants,
not only those with diabetes,
What about cholesterol?
Here's another umbrella review.
Although the authors concluded
that curcumin could have
ameliorating effects,
there was only
a half-point drop in LDL.
Lower doses may work better,
but a two-point drop
is still nothing
to write home about.
Turmeric curcumin
"blocks obesity" in mice
fed a high-fat diet.
What about people?
In an umbrella review of 50
randomized controlled trials,
curcumin supplementation
significantly decreased BMI,
body weight,
and waist circumference.
It was significant
statistically,
but how much of a difference
did it really make?
A loss of about a half kilogram
or a little more than a pound
of body weight.
Waist circumference,
a measure of abdominal obesity,
decreased by about a centimeter
and triple the effect in trials
with whole turmeric
relative to curcumin extracts.
So, for those with obesity
or type 2 diabetes
and wanting to lose weight,
the primary prescription
is lifestyle modification,
and some turmeric on the side
might be helpful
but may not make
that much difference.